<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The character of a good and bad subject, or, The duty of the people of England, Scotland, and Ireland manifestly proved by the word of God, wherein is made appear the fatal consequences of rebellious principles : in a sermon / preach'd by Constant Oates ...</title>
            <author>Oates, Constant.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 33 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 11 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53312</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O26</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17279</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13156298</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13156298</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98174</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53312)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98174)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The character of a good and bad subject, or, The duty of the people of England, Scotland, and Ireland manifestly proved by the word of God, wherein is made appear the fatal consequences of rebellious principles : in a sermon / preach'd by Constant Oates ...</title>
                  <author>Oates, Constant.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  N.T. --  Romans XIII, 1 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Obedience --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-11</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98174:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98174:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHARACTER OF A <hi>Good, and Bad, Subject:</hi> OR, THE Duty of the PEOPLE OF <hi>ENGLAND, SCOTLAND,</hi> and <hi>IRELAND;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Manifeſtly proved by the word of GOD; wherein is made appear the fatal Conſequences of REBELLIOUS PRINCIPLES: IN A SERMON Preach'd by <hi>Conſtant Oates,</hi> Preacher of the Goſpel.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 Epiſt. <hi>Pet.</hi> chap. 2. ver. 13.</bibl>
               <p>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lord's ſake: whether it be unto the King, as Supreme, or unto Governours, as thoſe that are ſent by Him.</p>
            </q>
            <q>
               <bibl>1 <hi>Pet</hi> 5. 5.</bibl>
               <p>Likewiſe, you younger ſubmit your ſelves to the elder: yea, all of you ſubmit one to another, and be cloathed with humility.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for the Author, 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:98174:2"/>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98174:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>TO THE PEOPLE Of <hi>ENGLAND, SCOTLAND,</hi> and <hi>IRELAND.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>UNto You, my fellow Countrey-men and Subjects, (or which ought ſo to be) I, who am not under thoſe capacities of Guifts as ſome Learned you may meet withal; yet, not meeting with the like Diſcourſe, I now think it convenient to preſent to publick view this ſmall Treatiſe, which indeed is, <hi>The Duty of all good and faithful Subjects, which love to live in Peace, both in Families and Nations:</hi> I have therefore here laid down <hi>the Duty of Subjects to their Prince,</hi> and of <hi>Children to Parents,</hi> and <hi>Servants to Maſters;</hi> And herein, I am perſwaded, lieth a great part of Chriſtiantity; and I am ſure, the Peace and Safety of a Nation, and eaſe to all Governments, both in Nations and Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>milies; for what diſquiet is that Family in, where there are ill <hi>Servants,</hi> or <hi>Children!</hi> And what Peace hath that Nation, which is full of Rebellious and ill men! <hi>Sirs,</hi> The weal of a Nation lies in good and quiet Subjects, and to live peacably and quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, is every mans Duty; therefore, the Apoſtle (in <hi>Heb.</hi> 12) enjoyns all men to that very duty of
<pb facs="tcp:98174:3"/>
Peace and Quietneſs; <hi>Follow Peace with all men,</hi> (ſays he) <hi>and Holineſs, without which none ſhall ſee God;</hi> And therefore, I recommend this Treatiſe to you, to ſhew you, ſo far forth as a good Subject and an <hi>Engliſh</hi> man ought to do, not queſtioning but it will be well accepted by ſome good Subjects; But, if it meets with any reſiſtance, I ſhall not think it to be, becauſe what I have here aſſerted is not Truth; Nevertheleſs, that perſon that ill re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents it, is not a good Subject, and cannot bear with the Doctrine of Obedience and Subjection ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to God or Mam. I am ſure here is nothing but what the word of God doth hold forth, and main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain; Therefore I ſhall be the leſs concern'd at the oppoſition it may meet with from Diſloyal or ill men; but where it meets with a good Subject, and an honeſt Heart, I fear not but it will be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable; And as for all others, I leave it to God and their own Conſciences to judge, whether this be not their Duty. And now, my good Brethren, Countrey-men, and fellow-Subjects, wherein I am ſhort in ſtirring you up to the duty herein aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted, make You it up by your own ingenuity, and Loyalty both to God and Man: which that you may do, is the Prayer of</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your fellow-Subject, <hi>C. O.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98174:3"/>
            <head>
               <q>
                  <bibl>ROM. 13. <hi>verſe</hi> 1.</bibl> Let every Soul be ſubject to the High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Powers, for there is no Power but of God: the Powers that be, are ordained of God; <hi>or, as the Margin has it,</hi> ordered of God.</q>
            </head>
            <p>BEfore I enter upon the words themſelves, I think it not amiſs to let you underſtand what ſort of people I am like to meet with, for it is impoſſible to pleaſe all men: peradventure this ſmall Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe may meet with ſome diſcontented Diſſenters, rather than Phanaticks, becauſe I will give it a more ſober term than mad-men, which, we know, the name implies; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I will not ſay, mad-men may meet with this; but ſome diſſatisfied Diſſenters may meet with it, who, up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the firſt view of the Text, will be apt to reflect on the Author, and ſay, that he is a Papiſt, Royalliſt, Tory, or ſuch-like; But let them ſay what they will, they may be ſure he is no Diſſenter, nor one of thoſe who will nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther obey God nor Man; But, if this ſmall Treatiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet with any ſuch, all that I ſhall ſay, is, that word of the Apoſtle, and one of the greateſt of the Apoſtles, in the verſe following my Text, <hi>(viz.) Whoſoever therefore reſiſteth</hi>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:98174:4"/>
               <hi>the Power, reſisteth the Ordinance of God; and they that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi> And this is all I ſhall ſay to ſuch at preſent; and now I ſhall fall to the words themſelves, wherein are theſe five things obſervable: <hi>1ſt.</hi> an Exhortation. <hi>2dly.</hi> the perſons exorted. <hi>3dly.</hi> the thing exhorted to. <hi>4thly.</hi> the perſons to whom this duty is due. <hi>5thly.</hi> the reaſons or argument of the whole. As <hi>1ſt.</hi> the exhortation, and that is, <hi>let; 2dly.</hi> the perſons, and that is, <hi>every ſoul. 3dly.</hi> the thing exhorted to, that is, <hi>be ſubject. 4thly.</hi> the perſons to whom this duty is due, that is, <hi>the Higher Powers. 5thly.</hi> and <hi>laſtly,</hi> the reaſon and argument of the whole, <hi>for there is no Power but of God: the Powers that be, are ordained of God. Let every ſoul be ſubject to the Higher Powers, for there is no Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer but of God: the Powers that be, are ordained of God.</hi> The Text being thus divided into five branches, or heads, I ſhall raiſe theſe five Doctrines ſeverally from them, and ſpeak ſomthing to each; The firſt Doctrine is, <hi>That it is the duty of every Goſpel-miniſter to teach the people to be in due ſubjection, and not in Rebellion.</hi> The <hi>2d.</hi> Doctrine is, <hi>That it is not only the duty of Ministers ſo to preach, but of every one ſo to be in due ſubjection.</hi> The <hi>3d.</hi> Doctrine is, <hi>That ſubjection doth become all men.</hi> The <hi>4th</hi> Doctrine is, <hi>That the Higher Powers ought to be ſubmitted unto.</hi> The <hi>5th.</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> Doctrine is, <hi>That God is the great Ordainer of all Powers.</hi> I ſhall treat of theſe in order, and will begin with the firſt of them, which is this, That it is the duty of every Goſpel-miniſter to teach people to be in due ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection, and not to ſow the ſeed of Rebellion amongſt them; which Doctrine I will handle thus; firſt, prove the Doctrine by the example of Apoſtles; Secondly, lay down
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:98174:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
the reaſons of this point; Thirdly, ſhew you the ill conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quences of non-ſubjection; Fourthly and laſtly, wind up the Doctrine with the Application. Firſt, I prove the firſt Doctrine, That it is the duty of every good Miniſter to teach the people to be in ſubjection; for which take theſe Texts of Scripture, with the example of ſo good an Apoſtle, and Miniſter of Jeſus, as <hi>Paul</hi> was. I ſhall not mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiply Texts, but theſe few, that by the mouth of two or three witneſſes every thing may be confirmed; The firſt Text is, <hi>Titus</hi> 3. verſe 1. <hi>Put them in mind to be in ſubjecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to Principalities and Powers, and to obey Magistrates, and to be ready to every good work;</hi> which Text doth plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly confirm this Doctrine; as if the Apoſtle ſhould ſay, or at leaſt-wiſe did know, that there would be ſome Rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious Ones in the world: Therefore he exhorts them to this Duty, eſpecially pointing at Magiſtrates; which <hi>to obey,</hi> he counts a <hi>good work; being ready</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>to every good work.</hi> That is the firſt Text I ſhall give you, to clear this point. I need not ſtand to give more; but however, take one or two more, for the further manifeſting this Truth, and this Text is very pertinent to our purpoſe, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 13. <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of man, for the Lord's ſake: whether it be unto the King, as Supreme, or unto Governours, as unto them that are ſent by him.</hi> The Apoſtle has this duty two or three times in this Epiſtle; as, in verſe 17. of the ſame chapter, where he enjoyns this duty with the fear of God; ſaying, <hi>Fear God, and honour the King;</hi> and then ſurely there is ſubjection, or ought to be, to that Perſon, whom (with the fear of God) we ought to honour. Thus you ſee how clear this Doctrine is, by the practice of the Apoſtles; for the Apoſtles did ſo preach
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98174:5"/>
and teach this Doctrine; and as they ſaw it was their duty, who did it by Divine Inſpiration, then ſurely it is the duty of Miniſters now ſo to teach; but how few do thus teach, I leave to God and their conſciences; For inſtead of prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching ſubmiſſion to Government, we have ſuch now-a-days which preach little elſe but Rebellion; But farther, one Text more, for the clearing and confirming of this good Truth, becauſe I would have none reflect upon the Author, for laying down every man's duty, and ſay, he hath taken that in hand which he cannot prove, take <hi>Heb.</hi> 3. 17. <hi>Obey them that rule over you, and ſubmit your ſelves.</hi> Thus you ſee this Doctrine clearly proved by the exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of the Apoſtles, who thus taught the people to be ſubject to thoſe that had Rule and Authority over them, and are not forgetful (as ſome are) of their duty to Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipalities and Powers; and therefore in the words of my Text the Apoſtle ſo Preacheth, <hi>Let every Soul be ſubject to the Higher Powers.</hi> Thus having prov'd the Doctrine, by the example of the Apoſtles who were the immediate Miniſters of Chriſt, and ſpake by Divine Authority, and immediate Revelation: I hope none will ſtand to oppoſe the Author in this great Truth, which is both for the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of themſelves and Poſterities; the ſettlement of Affairs, and the troubles they now bring upon themſelves. So much for the confirmation of the firſt Doctrine: I ſhall now come to the ſecond thing propounded, which is this, <hi>Why Miniſters ought thus to Preach;</hi> The firſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon is, becauſe the eyes of the people are much upon their Teachers, and are too apt to ſuck in ill principles; which is plainly demonſtrated by <hi>Achitophel,</hi> who had no ſooner councelled young <hi>Abſalom</hi> to raiſe Rebellion againſt his
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:98174:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
Father <hi>David,</hi> but preſently the poor inconſiderate mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude began to <hi>Aſſociate;</hi> (But (thanks be to God) the Councel of our modern <hi>Achitophel</hi> being defeated, he is fled;) wherefore I would adviſe our Miniſters not to go this way to work, to raiſe feuds among their Hearers; but, on the contrary, rather exhort them to Submiſſion and Obedience, to the Fear of God, and to the Honour of the King, and to perſwade them from Rebellious Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>murings, which is much for their Peace and Advantage; but otherwiſe, is unavoidable Deſtruction; that is the firſt Reaſon. A ſecond Reaſon is this. Miniſters ought to teach people to obey Man, eſpecially Magiſtrates; becauſe they do duly teach people, or at leaſtwiſe ought ſo to do, their duty towards God. And as there is a duty towards God, ſo there is a duty towards Man, and more eſpecially to Government; for they which will not obey man whom they ſee daily, how ſhall they obey God, whom they have not ſeen? Beſides, God requires this duty of us, and his word injoyns us to put people in mind of thoſe that Rule over them; this is a ſecond Reaſon. A third Reaſon is this. Due ſubjection to Government, produceth Peace, Safety, to a People and Nation; pray what hath been the ill conſequences of of non-ſubmiſſion in moſt parts, but Deſtruction, and Ruine both of Families, Towns and Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, where Prince and People do not agree? But, I know who ought to ſubmit, Servant, or Maſter; Prince, or People? Reaſon tells us, that Servants ought to obey, for then ſurely People ought to ſubmit to their Prince. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Servants, obey them that are your own: Maſters.</hi> So much for the reaſons of the Doctrin.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98174:6"/>
Now to the third thing propounded, and that is, <hi>the ill conſequences of the neglect of this duty of thus teaching people their duty of being ſubject.</hi> The ill conſequences are theſe; Firſt, it tends to the diſquiet of the people, whoſe minds are ſtirred up to Feuds and Animoſities one amongſt another; for there are ſome turbulent Preachers abroad, who, inſtead of preaching Submiſſion, preach contrari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; inſtead of preaching from Texts which ſhould hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble people, preach from thoſe Texts that tend to nothing but ſtirring them up to Feuds and Fears, and ſuggeſting into their minds evil things againſt Government, prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching from Texts which pleaſe their own fancies, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 149. ver. 8. <hi>Let us bind their Kings in Chains, and their Princes in Fetters of Iron;</hi> and other Texts, as <hi>Acts</hi> 4. ver. 26. <hi>The Kings of the Earth ſtand up againſt the Lord and his Chriſt.</hi> Theſe Texts men are too apt to preach from, which are of ill conſequence, and tend to nothing but ſtrife, as they handle them. There be many, let them take what Texts they will, they will have a fling at the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and incenſe people with one paſſage or other; and will be ſure to find fault with both Prince and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which is of very ill conſequence; who, inſtead of ſuch preaching, ought otherwiſe to preach, and to preach from ſuch Texts as tend to Peace; as that of the Apoſtle, which counſels to <hi>follow Peace with all men, and Holineſs, without which no man ſhall ſee God:</hi> Inſtead of railing againſt Government, ſhould ſupport it, which hath far better conſequences in them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>2dly.</hi> The neglect of not teaching people this duty of ſubjection, but on the contrary to unſettle the minds of people, it hath this ill conſequence in it, as, murthering
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98174:6"/>
one of another. What were the conſequences of our for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Contentions in the late Times of Rebellion, but mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering of one another? Pray God keep us from it now, in theſe our days, and let not Rebellion, that <hi>Sin of Witch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>craft,</hi> be ſowed amongſt us now, as it was amongſt thoſe which our former good Prince had, who took the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment by violence into their own hands; Men which were very ill-minded, that neither would obey God nor Man, but would be all Maſters, and no Servants; all Kings, and no Subjects; from which ſort of Pretenders to Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, <hi>good Lord deliver us.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>So much for the ill conſequences, which was the third thing propounded; Now I come to the <hi>4th.</hi> and laſt thing, which is the Application of this Doctrine, in which I ſhall do theſe three things; Firſt, ſpeak to pretended Miniſters; Secondly, to young men; Thirdly, to all in general.</p>
            <p>Firſt, to pretended Miniſters; If it be ſo, you are much too blame; and for ſhame leave off preaching Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, and preach Peace and Subjection to Government; for God hath called you to this. Beſides, the Apoſtle preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth hard to this duty of Subjection, <hi>Rom</hi> 13. ver. 5. <hi>Wherefore, you muſt needs be ſubject; not only for wrath,</hi> (as if he ſhould ſay, <hi>not only for fear,) but for conſcience-ſake.</hi> How can you pretend to be Miniſters of Chriſt indeed, when you, inſtead of preaching Peace, preach Rebellion? or, (as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>Philip.</hi> 1. ver. 10.) <hi>who preach Chriſt more out of contention, than ſincerity.</hi> Sirs, for ſhame leave off this preaching Chriſt; for it doth not only hinder your own Liberties, but the Liberties of others, who may and would live in Peace, and ſit under their own Vines in ſafety; ſince you have ſo good a Prince to rule over
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98174:7"/>
you. But ſecondly, I will ſay to you young men, who I would adviſe to be ſubject to your Prince; and, as God in his holy word in another ſence, ſence, <hi>Remember your Creator in the days of your youth:</hi> As God doth require your youthful ſubmiſſion to himſelf, ſo in your youth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful days be good Subjects to the Government you live under, and be not led away by ill-minded men. <hi>3dly.</hi> and <hi>lastly,</hi> One word in general, and ſo I conclude this firſt Doctrine; Be perſuaded to ſubmit to the Government we live under, <hi>fear God, and honour the King,</hi> and be loving Subjects; Serve him in <hi>Love,</hi> and not <hi>for Fear;</hi> in ſo doing you will be rewarded both of God and Man, and other Nations will admire at your Love and Loyalty to your Prince; Therefore now let us ſtrive to ſtir one another to <hi>fear God, honour the King,</hi> and <hi>love as Bretheren;</hi> ſo ſhall we live in Peace and Union one with another. So I come now to the ſecond Doctrine, <hi>That it is not only the duty of Miniſters ſo to preach, but of people to be in ſubjection: Lest every ſoul be in ſubjection.</hi> In the handling this Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, I ſhall but juſt hint at ſome Texts of Scripture, and ſo paſs to the reſt of the Doctrines which remain<hi>:</hi> inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding only to prove the Doctrines, becauſe it is the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication of the whole I intend to aim at. For the proof of the ſecond Doctrine, take theſe Texts; 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 5, 6. <hi>Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ye younger ſubmit your ſelves to the Elder; yea all of you be in ſubjection one to another.</hi> Thus you ſee the Apoſtles all preached this duty of ſubjection and humility one to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards another: How much more then ought we to be ſubject to Authority, and to <hi>give unto</hi> Caeſar <hi>that which is</hi> Caeſar<hi>'s; Honour, to whom Honour is due; Fear, to whom fear is due; Fear God, and honour the King;</hi> which is but
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98174:7"/>
your Duty ſo to do? So I paſs to the third Doctrine, which is this, <hi>That ſubjection becomes all men;</hi> for proof whereof take theſe Texts; <hi>Jam.</hi> 4. ver. 6. <hi>For God re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſisteth the prowd, and giveth grace to the humble. Coloſſ</hi> 2. 18. <hi>With all humbleneſs, of mind. Epheſ.</hi> 4. 2. <hi>With all meek-long ſuffering, forbearing one another in love.</hi> And our Lord Chriſt ſaith, <hi>(Matt.</hi> 23. 12.) <hi>He that humbleth himſelf ſhall be exalted.</hi> So that here we plainly ſee, that Subjection and Humility are Virtues becoming all men; and now I paſs to the fourth Doctrine, <hi>Who is that Higher Powers ought to be ſubmitted to?</hi> For which take theſe Texts of Scripture, <hi>Matt.</hi> 22. 17, 21. &amp; <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 7. <hi>Render there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore unto all their dues; Tribute, to whom Tribute is due; Cuſtom, to whom Cuſtom; Fear, unto whom Fear, Honour, unto whom Honour is due.</hi> And if you do but caſt your eye upon the fore-mentioned place of Scripture, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 17. the Apohle tells you to whom theſe things are due<hi>: Love the Brotherhood; fear God, and honour the King.</hi> Thus I have proved the fourth Doctrine, and now I come to the <hi>5th.</hi> and laſt Doctrine, which is this, <hi>That God is the great Ordainer of all Powers and Authorities;</hi> which if I make appear, (as I queſtion not) ſurely then theſe Powers ought to be obeyed; for God doth not give us Princes to Mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, nor Kings to Rebel againſt; But take theſe Texts for the proof of the <hi>5th.</hi> and <hi>laſt</hi> Doctrine, <hi>Act.</hi> 10. 42. and 13. 48. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 19. 14. &amp; 15. 24. <hi>Matt.</hi> 28. 18. <hi>All Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wer is given unto me in Heaven and in Earth,</hi> Matt. 6. 13. <hi>Thine is the Kingdom, and the Power.</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 7. <hi>For we have this Treaſure in Earthen Veſſels, that the Power might be of God, and not of us.</hi> Thus then we ſee that God is the Author of all Power, and that it is from Him that all
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98174:8"/>
Power and Authority is; He then that will not obey the Authority that God hath ſet over him, doth not o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bey God. Thus I have proved all the five Doctrines; now we come to the Application, which take as followeth; The firſt Uſe we make of theſe Doctrines, ſhall be of Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amination, and <hi>Characters of a good or bad Subject;</hi> The ſecond Uſe ſhall be the motives to preſs you to the duty of Subjection; The third Uſe ſhall be of Reprehenſion and Reproof. The firſt Uſe is of Examination<hi>:</hi> Is it ſo as we have heard, that <hi>every ſoul ought to be in ſubjection to the Higher Powers?</hi> Then let us examine our ſelves, whether we are good Subjects, yea, or no; which if we be, we are under theſe Characters; <hi>First,</hi> He that is a good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject, doth not only <hi>fear God,</hi> but <hi>honours and loves his King,</hi> and will not ſee Him abuſed, nor will do Him any hurt. This was the Caſe of <hi>David;</hi> though he might have deſtroyed his Lord, he would not; ſaying, <hi>How dare I do the Lord's Anointed any harm?</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 23. <hi>For the Lord delivered him into my hand, but I would not ſtretch forth my hand againſt the Lord</hi>'s <hi>Anointed.</hi> This is the firſt Character of a good Subject.</p>
            <p>The ſecond is this: A good Subject does not only love his Prince, but will lay down his Life for his Prince, and ſtand by him in all ſtreights, and will hate his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. See what Subjects <hi>David</hi> had, when he was forc'd to fly from Rebellious <hi>Abſalom:</hi> here is the Tryal and Love of a good Subject. See 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. ver. 30. <hi>And</hi> David <hi>went up by the aſcent of Mount</hi> Olivet, <hi>and wept as he went up, and had his head covered; and all the people that were with him covered every man his head, and went up, weeping as they went up.</hi> Here, Sirs, you ſee true Subjects
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:98174:8"/>
will not leave their Prince in ſtreights, but will rather ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer with him, weep with him, live with him, and die with him.</p>
            <p>The third Character is: A good Subject will not only live and die with him, but will, to the uttermoſt of his endeavour, deſtroy the King's Enemies, and lay out his Life, his Eſtate, and his All, for his Lord and Prince. Do but ſee how they came to the King to tell him of his Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies; ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 31. <hi>And they told</hi> David, Achito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phel <hi>is amongſt the Conſpirators. Sam.</hi> 16. 15, 16. This is the third Character.</p>
            <p>The fourth Character is this: A good Subject is of a good and willing nature, ready to bring, and run with good Tidings to the King. Do but ſee what good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects <hi>David</hi> had in his ſtreights, when his Rebellious Son, (as ſome now-a-days would do) even purſu'd him to death: No ſooner <hi>Joab,</hi> like a good Subject as he was, had deſtroy'd the King's Enemies, but they ran to bear the King Tidings, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 19. and almoſt to the end of that Chapter, you may ſee how ready they ran to bear the King Tidings; ver. 19. tells us to this effect: <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Himaaz <hi>the ſon of</hi> Zadock, <hi>Let me now run and bear the King tidings how the Lord hath avenged him of his enemies;</hi> And again (in ver. 22.) he ſaith, <hi>I pray thee let me run after</hi> Cuſhi; Nay, when <hi>Joab</hi> denied, yet he (ver. 23.) preſſes one to perſuade him, and ſaith, <hi>But however let me run;</hi> and <hi>Joab</hi> ſaid unto him <hi>Run:</hi> From whence it is worth obſerving, that a good Subject will not take any repulſe, but will, and is always willing to bring his Prince good Tidings. At the cloſe of this Chapter we do not only ſee their willingneſs, but the care they had of their
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98174:9"/>
meſſage to the King, for fear of diſpleaſing or grieving him; Therefore <hi>Cuſhi,</hi> when the King ask'd him, (ver. 29.) <hi>Is the young man ſafe?</hi> he, to mitigate the King's grief, anſwers him prudently, and with great care, (putting him in mind of his Enemies) and makes him this reply, <hi>The enemies of my Lord the King, and all that riſe up againſt thee to do thee hurt, be as the young man is.</hi> Thus now we ſee not only the willingneſs of a good Subject running to bring the King Tidings, But alſo the care and tenderneſs they have of him. This is the fourth Character.</p>
            <p>I now come to the fifth Character of a good Subject, which is the laſt I ſhall give at this time: A good Subject is troubled and grieved at the Exilement of his Prince, and will not be ſatisfied till he is returned to his Throne; Nay, a good Subjects voice, as the voice of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> (1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. 19.) <hi>We will have a King to reign ever us;</hi> they were not ſatisfied till they had a King to ſubmit to, and they are not willing to part with him, much leſs then would they murder him; No, but on the contrary would mourn for their King's Exilement, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 19. 24, 30. <hi>And</hi> Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phiboſheth <hi>the ſon of</hi> Saul <hi>came to meet the King, and had neither dreſſed his feet, nor trimmed his beard, nor waſhed his cloaths, from the day the King departed, until the day he came again in peace.</hi> Thus you ſee how a good Subject doth ſit in a diſconſolate condition while his Prince is in Exilement; and is not only thus ſad for his Exilement, but will rejoyce at his return<hi>:</hi> ſee ver. 30. where he ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereth theſe words, <hi>Yet let him take all, foraſmuch as my Lord the King is come again in peace unto his own houſe.</hi> Theſe are the Characters of a good Subject; Therefore let us examine our ſelves which of us loves our Prince as theſe did.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98174:9"/>
So much for the Characters of good Subjects. I come now to the Characters of a bad Subject, Therefore, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he cannot be called a Subject that is Rebellious, I will put it into theſe terms, <hi>The Characters of the King's Enemies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He is an Enemy to the King and Government he lives under, that, like <hi>Shimei,</hi> curſes the King, and takes ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to do it when the King is in ſtreights. Do but ſee that wicked Enemy of the King, when he ſaw his Lord forc'd to leave his own houſe, goes and curſeth him, and reviles him, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 5, <hi>&amp;c. And thus ſaid</hi> Shimei <hi>when he curſed, Come out thou bloudy man, thou man of</hi> Belial; and in the <hi>8th.</hi> verſe, he tells the King, <hi>Thou art a bloudy man:</hi> So that you may ſee what the King's Enemies will do, when they ſee their King in ſtreights.</p>
            <p>I come now to the ſecond Character of an Enemy to the King, which is this; They will not only be Enemies to the King, but all that belongs to him. Do but ſee how they chas'd this preſent Prince from his Father's houſe, and made him fly to an Oak for refuge, and ſought his Life too if they could have found him, for his Fathers would not do, as late experience hath made manifeſt to us, whom God preſerve from the hands of ſuch Enemies. But take Scripture for this Character, that they hate not only the King, but his Friends; for I am reſolved to ſay nothing but what experience and Scripture makes appear; ſee 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 17. 12. it is <hi>Huſhai</hi>'s Counſel to defeat <hi>Achitophel;</hi> but how ready we ſee the King's Enemies are to hearken to it<hi>: So ſhall we come upon him in ſome place where he ſhall be found, and we will light upon him as the dew falleth on the ground; and of him and all that are with him there ſhall</hi>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:98174:10"/>
               <hi>not be left ſo much as one man.</hi> Now ſee what the King's Enemies reply to this; <hi>And all the men of</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſaid, The counſel of</hi> Huſhai <hi>is better than the counſel of</hi> Achitophel. Thus you ſee how ready they are to take counſel againſt the King; ſo we end with the ſecond Character of an Enemy to the King.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Character is this<hi>:</hi> He that is an E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemy to the King, will not ſtick to abuſe him, as we have heard already; but would, like that wicked Enemy, ſlay him at once; ſee 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 26. 8. <hi>Then ſaid</hi> Abiſhai <hi>to</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>God hath delivered thine Enemy into thine hand this day: Now therefore let me ſmite him, I pray thee, with this Spear, even to the ground, at once, and I will not ſmite him the ſecond time;</hi> But <hi>David,</hi> like a good Subject, ſaid, <hi>Deſtroy him not;</hi> But this Murdering King-killing Enemy pretends Religion for his work, and tells <hi>David, The Lord hath delivered him into thine hand,</hi> and calls him <hi>David</hi>'s Enemy, to heighten his hatred againſt him. Thus you ſee men that are Enemies to the King, will rather then miſs of their intent, do any thing; and they have Religion for a Cloak and Hood-wink for their Violency; and therefore ſaith he, <hi>The Lord hath delivered him into thine hand, therefore, I pray thee, let me ſlay him.</hi> Thus I have done with the Characters of thoſe black Enemies to Kings and Governments, and ſhall ſay no more but theſe words of <hi>David, Can any man ſmite the Lords Anointed and be guiltleſs?</hi> This is the firſt Uſe, which is a Uſe of Examina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and Characters of a good or bad Subject: I now come to the ſecond uſe, which is of thoſe motives I pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to give you to preſs you to the duty here injoyned; The firſt motive is this: Conſider, that Subjection is
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98174:10"/>
commanded and required of you, both by the Law of God and Man; Beſides, look and ſee what Rebellion has done; It has murdered a good Prince already; therefore when your Anceſtors have been Diſloyal, be you the more Dutiful, and part not with one grain of your Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty; Conſider, what becomes of Rebellious men, but Death and Deſtruction; be not of thoſe whom the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle ſpeaks of, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 10. <hi>That walk after the Fleſh, in the Lust of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ncleanneſs; deſpiſers of Government; Perni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious are they; they are afraid to ſpeak evil of Dignities.</hi> What a ſad thing is this! And what an age we live in, when there needs ſo much Loyalty and Love! Therefore be perſuaded to love God and honour the King, and be not of a Rebellious mind, but be of the mind of thoſe in 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 16. 15, 16. Theſe were men of a good and loving nature to their Prince, and were ready at all turns to ſerve him. And therefore be perſuaded to be of thoſe that will lay down their Lives and Eſtates for the King.</p>
            <p>Conſider what Rebellious perſons bring upon them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; nothing but Death and Deſtruction at one time, or place, or other. You may read how <hi>Abſalom</hi> was caught up by the hair of the head for his Rebellion. Sirs, God hates Rebellion, and Rebellion is worſe than the Sin of Witchcraft; it breeds nothing but Deſtruction; There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore be perſuaded to this your duty, ſeeing God calls for it from you.</p>
            <p>Thirdly<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> The third motive is this, and that is to you young men. Learn to know your Prince; for as there is a duty to a Parent due from you, ſo there is a Duty and Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>legiance to your Prince; and I hope I may ſay, that there is not One in Ten thouſand in <hi>England, Scotland</hi> or
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98174:11"/>
               <hi>Ireland,</hi> but what are loving Subjects; If not, I wiſh they were known; for it is a ſhame to <hi>England</hi> to have a bad Subject, ſince they have ſo good a Prince, who loves to ſee his People in Peace and Quiet; for herein lies all our happineſs, that we can ſay in reality what others did ſay fainedly to <hi>Abſalom,</hi> God Save the King.</p>
            <p>The third and laſt Uſe is a Uſe of Reprehenſion and Reproof to thoſe that dare be ſo bold as to be Diſloyal, and ſpeak againſt Government; I dare be bold to tell ye, You deſerve death here, if you have it not hereafter; Therefore I ſhall cloſe with the words of the Apoſtle, and then let any be bold if they dare; which words are theſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13. 2. <hi>Whoſoever therefore reſisteth the Power, reſiſteth the Ordinonce of God: and they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves Damnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
